Register of the Lulu Ryan Rolston papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lulu Ryan Rolston papers,
1912-1954
1914-1918
2006C7
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 7 oversize boxes, 1 framed caricature (5.4 linear feet)
Personal documents, newspaper issues, scrapbooks, photographs, and postcards relating to Allied nursing in France during World War I.
Rolston, Lulu Ryan, 1890-1980
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
April 23, 1889 Born, Rouses Point, New York
1914 Graduated from the New York Hospital
1915-1916 Nurse at American Ambulance Hospital of Paris
1916 Taught the Carrell-Dakin Method in the United States
1917 Worked at Ellis Island, New York
1917-1919 Nurse at New York Hospital, Base #9 A.E.F. Hospital in France
1918 Decorated with the Medaille des Epidemies
1919 Discharged and sailed for the U.S. on the George Washington
1920-1930 Public Health Nurse for the City of Los Angeles
1940 Served as WWII nurse
1980 Honored by President Jimmy Carter in recognition of services to the U.S. Armed Forces
1980 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains a series of mementos from Lulu Rolston’s time at the American Ambulance Hospital of Paris the and New York Base #9 Hospital in France. Assigned to the New York Base #9 Hospital, Rolston worked as an Allied nurse during World War I. Rolston treated soldiers wounded in the Meuse-Argonne Offensive, which was one of the largest battles in U.S. military history. The collection highlights her time as an Allied nurse with a series of personal documents, newspapers, scrapbooks, photographs, and postcards. A number of her husbands, Howard Rolston’s, photographs and documents are also included in the collection. Howard Rolston was an enlisted soldier in France while Lulu Rolston worked at the New York Base #9 Hospital. The bulk of the collection involves Lulu Rolston's work in and around France. The collection contains documents written in French. Box one includes an inventory of the collection.
United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; Nursing--France.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Personal documents file, 1914-1926
  Scope and Contents
  Materials include documents from both the American Ambulance and New York Base #9 Hospitals, spanning the years 1914 to 1916. Items include poems, a small diary, bulletins, certificates, and a book about the New York Base #9 Hospital. The New York Hospital in France Base Hospital No. 9 A.E.F. contains handwritten notes by Lulu Rolston. The items include documents written in French. Documents correspond with No. 3 on the inventory list.
  - American Ambulance Hospital, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - New York Hospital, 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - The New York Hospital in France, Base Hospital No. 9 A.E.F., 1920 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - The Night was Cold and the Wind Did Blow, 1920 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Photographs and postcards, 1915-1919, 1954
  Includes photographs from the New York Base #9 Hospital and postcards from the American Ambulance Hospital. Photographs and postcards feature nurses, doctors, soldiers, hospital grounds, living quarters, burial sites, and social events within the two hospitals from 1915 to 1919. Postcards contain personal messages written to Lulu Rolston in 1954. Photographs and postcards correspond with No. 3 on the inventory list.
  - New York Hospital, Cornell Medical College, 1954 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - American Ambulance Hospital, 1915 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - The New York Hospital in France, Base #9 A.E.F, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 1:7-8)
- Album of patient letters, 1916-1919 (Box 2)
  Album contains letters, drawings, notebooks, and maps sent to Lulu Rolston in France from 1916 to 1919. Maps include East France/Germany and Luxembourg and “IV Armee” TAHURE (Marne), second battle of 1918. The album corresponds with No. 1 on the inventory list.
- Lulu Rolston scrapbook, 1915-1919 (Box 5)
  Scrapbook contains photographs, certificates, assignment letters, and service documents relating to Lulu and Howard Rolston from 1915 to 1919. Locations include both the American Ambulance and New York Base #9 Hospitals. Many of the photographs include enlisted soldiers and their camps. The scrapbook was assembled by Lauren Rolston Petterson. The scrapbook corresponds with No. 2 on the inventory list.
- New York Base Hospital #9, 1915-1919 (Box 9)
  Album contains newspapers articles, maps, service documents, postcards, and handwritten notes from 1915 to 1919. The service documents pertain to Lulu and Howard Rolston. Throughout the album, Lulu Rolston wrote brief descriptions and notes alongside the photographs, which include her personal connection to the photograph and memories about the location. The album corresponds with No. 4 on the inventory list.
- American Ambulance Hospital album, 1915-1916 (Box 3)
  Album details Lulu Rolston’s time at the American Ambulance Hospital in Neuilly-sur-Seine through a series of photographs from 1915 to 1916. Photographs within the album include trips across France, time spent on the ship she traveled on, and soldiers within the hospital. The album corresponds with No. 5 on the inventory list.
- New York Base #9 Hospital album, 1918 (Box 8)
  Album contains photographs of the nurses and doctors Lulu Rolston lived with while working at the New York Base #9 Hospital in 1918. The album corresponds with No. 6 on the inventory list.
- Lulu and Howard Rolston's postcards, 1914-1918 (Box 4)
  Includes an album of postcards Lulu and Howard Rolston collected while in France from 1914 to 1918. The postcards include a series of images of monuments, landmarks, churches, statues, and graves in France. Many of the images include locations within the American Ambulance Hospital grounds. One postcard series includes La Grande Guerre. The album corresponds with No. 7 on the inventory list.
- Howard Rolston's photographs and postcards, 1916-1918 (Box 7)
  Album contains a series of photographs and postcards from 1916 to 1918. Photographs include images of Howard Rolston while stationed in France. Postcards include images of monuments, churches, hotels, and a series of Paris locations. One postcard series within the album include F. Chapeau, Nantes. The album corresponds with No. 9 on the inventory list.
- World War I Photographs album, 1912-1918 (Box 8)
  Album contains a series of photographs from 1912 to 1918. Photographs include images of various locations Rolston traveled to in France and the United States. Photographs taken in the United States include family photographs. Photographs taken in France highlight locations traveled as a nurse while working at the New York Base #9 Hospital. The album corresponds with No. 11 on the inventory list.
- Newspapers, 1916-1919 (Box 6)
  Newspapers include The Sewanee Purple, Qu'est-ce Ques C'est, and The Stars and Stripes. All three newspapers were published during World War I, between the years 1916 to 1919. Two Emprunt de la defense nationale posters can be found within the materials. The Sewanee Purple was published by Sewanee, the University of the South in Tennessee. The majority of the newspapers are issues of The Stars and Stripes, the official newsletter of the American Expeditionary Forces (A.E.F.) in France. The Qu'est-ce Que C'est newspaper was published by American students of the University of Toulouse. The series of newspapers corresponds with No. 8 on the inventory list.
- Framed Caricature, 1939
  Drawn by George Shellhas, the cartoon caricature titled “Base Hospital 9" was given to Lulu Rolston at a World War I reunion in 1939. The drawing depicts a Base Hospital #9 soldier wielding a knife at a man holding a Peace Pact document and a soldier yelling “Kamerad!” The caricature corresponds with No. 10 on the inventory list.